U.S. President's Railroad Commission Photographs 5003 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Series XI: Illinois Central Railroad: Memphis Division
  - Industrial Siding, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 10)
    Illustrates poor housekeeping. Notice how the weeds along the right-of-way obscure the rail and also obscure anything that may be along the track. Clearances are very close. The tracks are blocked by automobile and truck traffic as you can see from the picture. Notice the truck parked on the tracks in the center rear of the picture. Notice also the very close clearance between the truck shown in the far left and the box car shown to its right. Notice also this is quite a hilly area and therefore it's necessary for the box cars to have the brakes set. These tracks are on Tennessee Street in the terminal. They run right in the middle of a public street for half a mile, around a curve in the street. First-class freight trains travel this route, as well as switch engines, with numerous industries, all of which are protected by the fireman, whose responsibilities include taking all the signals in spotting cars, protecting the property of the railroad and the public alike.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 10)
  - Freight Cars, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 11)
    We see a picture of the Memphis Terminal. Shown is a crossing used by several railroads. The fireman has the responsibility of keeping the engineer informed of trains using the crossing while the engineer is taking signals from yard crews on the other side. The crossing is shown in the background of the picture in the center, immediately in front of the locomotive.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 11)
  - Blind Crossing That is Heavily Traveled, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 12)
    Also in the Memphis Terminal. Shows another blind crossing that is heavily traveled. Here again we have a problem of automobiles parked very close to the track. Clearance is close on the fireman's side along these tracks. As you can see from the picture, there is a good deal of travel across this crossing.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 12)
  - Layout of Yard Approaching Frisco Wye, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 13)
    This picture taken in the Memphis terminal shows the lay-out of the yard with an engine approaching the Frisco Wye. The fireman is depended upon to keep the engineer informed of the conditions on the track and the movement of other engines. This is a 24-hour a day, day and night operation in a very busy area. There is a number of switch engines working here at all times and there is a great number of employees that work in the industries around this area.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 13)
  - Freight Cars, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 14)
    We see a picture of the Memphis terminal. Shown is a crossing used by several railroads. The fireman has the responsibility of keeping the engineer informed of trains using the crossing while the engineer is taking signals from yard crews on the other side. The crossing is shown in the background of the picture in the center, immediately in front of the locomotive.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 14)
  - Congestion of Crossover Tracks, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 15)
    Illinois Central Railroad Unit No. 472 in yard near Vaiden Warehouse (699 So. Main Street). This picture of the Memphis terminal shows the congestion of cross-over tracks and also interlocking systems that require the close attention of the fireman to prevent accidents. Notice particularly the sharp curve to the right shown in the center foreground.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 15)
  - Congestion of Crossover Tracks, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 16)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 16)
  - Industrial Siding and Cross-over Tracks, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 17)
    Stratton Warren Hardware Company (37 E. Carolina Avenue). Shows a very hazardous condition at the Memphis yards. As you can see, there are two cross-overs, one in the foreground and one towards the rear. These conditions require look-out by all members of the crew at all times. There are several railroads that use these cross-over tracks. Notice also how a road runs right next to the railroad tracks shown in the center towards the background of the picture. You can just see the light colored car behind the telephone pole.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 17)
  - Industrial Siding and Cross-over Tracks, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 18)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 18)
  - Grade Crossing, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 19)
    J.R. Watkins Company (70 West Crump Boulevard). We see a grade crossing in the Memphis terminal. All signals in this area must be passed on the fireman's side. Note the debris scattered along the right-of-way, and the cars parked near the tracks.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 19)
  - Congestion of Crossover Tracks, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 20)
    Here the switching lead crosses the Wye and visibility is very poor. We see the box car left in a bad position where it may be fouling the track immediately to its left. A condition such as this demands someone on the left side of the engine to watch the clearance. (Ssimilar location to Exhibits V-8 and V-8A).
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 20)
  - Industrial Siding and Grade Crossing, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 21)
    National Rose Furniture Warehouse (767 Kentucky Street at Railroad Avenue)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 21)
  - Industrial Siding and Grade Crossing, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 22)
    National Rose Furniture Warehouse (767 Kentucky Street at Railroad Avenue). Another view showing particularly poor housekeeping. Notice how weeds have grown up along the right-of-way. In fact, the situation is so bad that it is difficult to see the rail running along the right. See how the road parallels the tracks. There is a good deal of traffic along this road as shown by the numbers of cars parked on the left side of the picture and also by the fact that there is a stop-and-go light along the road in the background.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 22)
  - Night Shot, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 23)
    Industrial siding
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 23)
  - Night Shot With Railroad Crossing Sign, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 24)
    Night view of the Memphis terminal. Switching is done constantly across the heavily used road crossing. All signals are passed on the fireman's side. Because of the surrounding light in the area, it's very difficult to see signals at nighttime. You have got to pick out one signal light to keep your eye on and you have to keep close watch on that light so that at all times you are sure that you are receiving the signal from your crew and not from a crew working nearby. Of course, this requires extra concentration on the part of the fireman.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 24)
  - Night Shot, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 25)
    Close clearance
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 25)
  - Southern Wye (center) and Frisco Wye (on left), 1960 (Box 56, Folder 26)
    Illinois Central passenger car to right in photo (cannot be certain of identification). (Same as photographs Internal Nos.14, 17, and 31) The sharp curve in the center to the right of the picture is known as Southern Wye. This wye is used to go east on Broadway (Railroad) Avenue while making transfer delivery to foreign railroads. Approximately 1/2 mile of this track on Broadway is interlocking plant. The remaining track, traveling through the heart of Memphis, over public crossings and crossing two main lines of foreign railroads, is approximately five miles in length. Track leading from center to left is known as Frisco Wye. This wye crosses at approximately 60 degrees angles the Frisco, Missouri Pacific, and Rock Island Main Lines, that are visible only from the fireman's side. The three main lines mentioned above are arranged so that there is a sharp curve after leaving the bridge that spans the Mississippi River. Crews using this track can only see approximately one city block, which is hardly enough visibility for such a congested area (in use by six class-1 railroads with train consists of as many as six diesel units and 150 to 225 cars).
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 26)
  - Kimberly Clark Building, North Memphis, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 27)
    Shows cars being spotted in the Kimberly Clark building with the fireman receiving signals.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 27)
  - Industrial Siding, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 28)
    Taken in the Memphis terminal. This is a congested area. Notice the weeds growing up along the right-of-way. In the picture we see a very dangerous cross-over. Trains crossing the road, which has the stop lights, have poor visibility due to the buildings, which are shown in the center of the photograph. Notice also how automobiles are parked near the tracks. This requires close observation from both sides of the engine to be sure that everything is clear for safe operation. Notice also how the roads leading from the foreground to the rear of the picture parallel the track. There is always the danger of a car or a truck getting too close to a passing train.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 28)
  - Frisco Locomotive 309, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 29)
    Shows an engine at a crossing. Here again we have the problem of debris and weeds along the tracks. Everybody has to keep a sharp look-out for debris that might derail the engine. There are no signs at this crossing.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 29)
  - Industrial Siding and Grade Crossing, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 30)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 30)
  - Beale Street Industry Track and Freight House, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 31)
    Bridge across Mississippi River in background. This is Beale Street industry track and team track. A constant lookout is imperative on account of frequent pedestrian and automobile traffic. Trucks block vision and hamper movements at all times. Note how the lead is cut into the main line going north. All these movements are on the fireman's side, even when fouling the main line.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 31)
  - River Front of Memphis Terminal, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 32)
    Taken along the riverfront of the Memphis terminal. Note the weeds obscuring the tracks causing poor footing and obstructing visibility of debris on the track. The tracks which lead in and out of the Beale Street Freight House of the Illinois Central are frequently blocked by transport trucks. You can see the close clearances in the freight house shown in the rear of the picture.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 32)
  - The "New Track", 1960 (Box 56, Folder 33)
    Shows part of a track in the Memphis terminal known as the "New Track" in Beale Street territory. This section shows very poor housekeeping, evidenced by the weeds along the right-of-way. Note also the treacherous footing. An example is the loose board in the center foreground along the tracks. This creates a bad condition for any one who is compelled to jump on and off moving cars and demands special vigilance on the part of the fireman. Notice also how the road runs right along by the track. You can see several points at which the tracks cross over the road. These crossings are not protected in any way. The driver of automobiles know that there are railroad tracks and railroad trains here, but cars seldom hesitate to look to see whether there are any trains coming. Moreover, the clearances are very close. not more than two or three feet, as you can see from the picture. A trainman riding on a car has to be observed carefully by all employees to ensure safe operation.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 33)
  - Southern Wye (center) and Frisco Wye (on left), 1960 (Box 56, Folder 34)
    Illinois Central passenger car to right in photo (cannot be certain of identification). (Same as photographs Internal Nos. 14, 17, and 23) The sharp curve in the center to the right of the picture is known as Southern Wye. This wye is used to go east on Broadway (Railroad) Avenue while making transfer delivery to foreign railroads. Approximately 1/2 mile of this track on Broadway is interlocking plant. The remaining track, traveling through the heart of Memphis, over public crossings and crossing two main lines of foreign railroads, is approximately five miles in length. Track leading from center to left is known as Frisco Wye. This wye crosses at approximately 60 degrees angles the Frisco, Missouri Pacific, and Rock Island Main Lines, that are visible only from the fireman's side. The three main lines mentioned above are arranged so that there is a sharp curve after leaving the bridge that spans the Mississippi River. Crews using this track can only see approximately one city block, which is hardly enough visibility for such a congested area (in use by six class-1 railroads with train consists of as many as six diesel units and 150 to 225 cars).
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 34)
  - Blind Crossing, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 35)
    In the Memphis terminal. Notice that the crossing here is completely blind from all directions due to the buildings on all sides of the crossing. Therefore it is practically impossible to see oncoming traffic until you are almost on the crossing. The street shown is a dead end. There is quite a bit of traffic here due to the industries in the area. You can see the large number of cars parked along the street and at the foot of the street shown in the rear of the picture.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 35)
  - Kimberly Clark Building, North Memphis, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 36)
    Clearance between train and wall minimal; engineer side. Shows close clearances in the Kimberly Clark building. The footing is bad. The switching shown is inside a building where close watch at all times is necessary to ensure the safety of the men working on the ground. Signals are passed on the fireman's side. Notice the debris lying on the tracks between the engine and the wall.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 36)
  - Kimberly Clark Building, North Memphis, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 37)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 37)
  - Kimberly Clark Building, Track No. 3, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 38)
    IC Unit 427 is on track No. 3, leading out of Kimberly Clark industry. All moves are made from the fireman's side. It is impossible for an engineer to get a signal at any time.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 38)
  - Sharp Curve Near Homes, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 39)
    Locomotive No. 309 & National RoseTruck. Engineer and firemen must watch out for children. We see a sharp curve around towards the right. Signals must be given on the fireman's side. Just at the point of the curve there is a heavily traveled automobile crossing. As you can see there are homes running close by which create a hazard because of the possibility of children running on the tracks.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 39)
  - Place in Yard Where Light is Provided by Kerosene Lamps at Switches, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 40)
    Shows a general view of the tracks at Memphis, Tennessee. The signal shown opposite the switches in the picture are lit up at night by old-fashioned kerosene lamps, not by electric lights. Frequently because of the wind and the vibration these lights are out at night and therefore the engineer and fireman have to rely upon being able to see the switch points in order to determine how the switches are lined. Note also the houses close to the track which of course poses the hazard of children running out from the houses onto the track. You notice that there are no fences along the right-of-way to keep off children. Notice also on right side of picture the footpath for pedestrians. In fact, one pedestrian can be seen walking along the path which parallels the tracks. Note also the numerous sharp curves leading off to the left rear and farther back towards the right rear.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 40)
  - Industry Siding, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 41)
    Taken in Helena, Arkansas and shows a particularly dangerous situation: an oil tank spotted at an industry. Just beyond the oil tank you can see a road crossing which is used by employees of the company and by passenger cars. There is no warning whatsoever that there is a railroad track at this point. Moreover, the view of the automobiles is cut off by the buildings on each side of the street.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 41)
  - Industry Siding, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 42)
    Taken in Helena, Arkansas and shows a particularly dangerous situation--an oil tank spotted at an industry there. Just beyond the oil tank you can see a road crossing which is used by employees of the company and by passenger cars. There is no warning whatsoever that there is a railroad track at this point. Moreover, the view of the automobiles is cut off by the buildings on each side of the street.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 42)
  - Kimberly Clark Building, North Memphis, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 43)
    This view was taken while switching Kimberly Clark in North Memphis. All signals are taken on the fireman's side. This plant is completely switched three times a day, seven days a week. There are nine tracks to switch and spot. Sometimes as many as 125 cars are handled in an eight-hour period. N-37 shows spotting cars in track #4 which holds approximately 5 cars, all enclosed under a building with nothing but a trick wall and wheel stops at the end of the rail. There are seven of such tracks that are enclosed under a roof and all signals are taken on the fireman's side.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 43)
  - Spur Track, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 44)
    Shows a spur track in Clarksdale, Mississippi. This spur track leads back into several industries. By observation you can see the poor housekeeping here as shown by the overgrowth of weeds along the right-of-way. Naturally, a sharp look-out must be kept under these conditions for debris that might cause a derailment or other damage to the train. Along this track there are several crossings that are not protected. One crossing is used a great deal, and, as the picture shows, the view of the locomotive coming out of this spur track is blocked by the two buildings shown in the picture, one on each side of the track.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 44)
  - Track Leading to River, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 45)
    Ferry operation between Trotters Point, MS and Helena, AK. Photo taken on Trotter Point side. Another picture of the incline down to the float on the way to Helena-Trotters Point of ferry.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 45)
  - Passenger Platform, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 46)
    Shows the passenger platform tracks at Clarksdale. It is essential to maintain a sharp watch-out here because passengers frequently cross the tracks on the way to the platform shown to the left of the picture. Notice also the sharp curve to the right.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 46)
  - Industrial Siding, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 47)
    Delta Grocery & Cotton Co. Shows an industrial track at Clarksdale, Mississippi. The picture shows two unprotected crossings, one in the foreground and one in the rear toward the Delta Grocery and Cotton Company. Notice how close the Ford Truck is parked to the track, making it imperative to maintain a sharp lookout. The general public makes great use of the crossings because of the vicinity of the grocery house. Also, it is in the vicinity of the Illinois Central Depot. Passenger automobiles are parked on and close to racks. There are several points on this track where automobiles are parked so close to the right-of-way that there is danger of side-swiping them. Naturally movement is made along this track both in the daytime and at night and in rainy and stormy weather.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 47)
  - Tracks Leading to a Float, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 48)
    We see tracks leading to a "float" or ferry across the Mississippi River. This picture is taken at Trotters Point, Mississippi, and shows a view of the track leading down to the float. Note here the heavy undergrowth along the right-of-way and the obstruction by the small building used by the track maintenance department. Due to the undergrowth of this building all signals are given on the fireman's side at this particular point. The way the switching is handled at Trotters Point is as follows: the cars are pulled by the engine from Clarksdale, Mississippi to Trotters Point. At Trotters Point there are three switch tracks. The reason for this is that it is necessary to line the cars up so that the maximum number of cars possible can be put on the float. Also, it is necessary to put the cars in front of the engine so that the cars can be pushed on the float. If there is a great deal of back and forth switching at Trotters Point there is a great number of obstructions which make it absolutely essential to maintain a watch on both sides of the locomotive.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 48)
  - Tracks Leading to a Float, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 49)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 49)
  - Locomotive Pulling out of Wye, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 50)
    IC Unit No. 601. We see a view of Clarksdale, Mississippi. The locomotive shown in the picture is pulling out of what is known as the Wye. As shown in the picture, as the engineer pulls around his view in front of him is completely obstructed by the curve and he has to rely entirely upon the fireman to maintain a lookout as to what is in front of the engine.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 50)
  - Industrial Siding, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 51)
    Cotton bales. Close clearance. Taken at Clarksdale, Mississippi. Note how the underbrush is permitted to grow up around the tracks and even to obscure the tracks. It's important to maintain a very close watch where these conditions exist and to spot debris on the ground that might cause a derailment. The loading platform shown in the picture is used not only for railroad employees in this area, but also by other persons. It is the duty of the fireman and the engineer to make sure that all personnel, railroad and non-railroad, are out of the way before a car is moved.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 51)
  - Tracks Leading to River, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 52)
    Ferry operation between Trotters Point, MS and Helena, AK. Photo taken from Arkansas side. Taken over on the other Arkansas side of the Mississippi River and shows the incline on that side which leads down to the ferry. Here again notice the poor housekeeping on the incline. Observe the weeds growing up along the right of way. The concrete retaining wall shown on the left side of the picture and the concrete wall shown on the right side of the picture both cut down visibility and make it essential to have a look-out on both sides of the locomotive. You will notice a footpath in the middle of the track that leads from incline to the sea wall. This is used by pedestrians going to and from the river. Because the sea wall blocks the view of both pedestrians and the engine crew it is most important to keep close observation in order to prevent injury to pedestrians in this area. Float operations are carried out across the Mississippi River in all kinds of weather. Vision is often times obstructed by dense fog.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 56, Folder 52)
  - Tracks Leading to Mississippi River, 1960 (Box 56, Folder 53)